Register of the Hugh Gibson papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL, 1906-1956 (Boxes 140-152, on shelf)
  - Diplomas
    - Ecole Libre des Sciences Politiques, Paris: Diploma of the diplomatic section, 1907
    - Pomona College, California: M.A., and L.L.D., 1918 1929
    - Universite de Louvain, Belgium: Doctor of Diplomacy and Political Science, 1928
    - Universite Libre de Bruxelles, Belgium: Doctor of Law, 1930
    - Yale University, New Haven: Doctor of Law, 1931
  - Humoristic diploma presented to Gibson by Herman A. Webster, Paris, 1907
  - Checkbooks (Box 141)
  - Daily reminders and address books (Box 142)
    - Of Hugh Gibson, 1940-1953
    - Of Ynes Gibson, 1945-1950 (Box 143)
  - Autograph books (Box 144)
    - Undated
    - 1906-1912
    - 1914-1915
    - 1922-1938
    - 1928-1938
    - 1932
    - 1942-1956
  - Autograph book, 1940-1942 (Box 145)
  - Appointment book, 1922
  - Guest lists book, 1928-1933
  - Sitting arrangements book, 1927-1932
  - Note book, undated
  - Note books of courses at the Ecole Libre des Sciences Politiques, Paris
    - Diplomatic history
    - The Oriental question
    - Political science
    - International law (2 vols.)
  - Leatherbound book of signatures by British women in thanks for Gibson's attempts to save Nurse Cavell in 1914, 1932 June 23
  - Souvenir photo album entitled "Belgian War Mission, July 1917"
  - Two Speeches on Italy's Foreign Policy, Rome (inscribed to Gibson from Dino Grandi), 1930
  - Au banquet des Nations: The League at Lunch (sketches of various conferences by Derso & Kelen), Geneva, 1937
  - Medals and decorations (Box 146)
    - Belgium
      - "Je Maintiendrai"
      - The Order of Leopold: "L'Union Fait la Force,", 1832
      - "De la Reine Elizabeth,", 1916
      - "Comite National de Secours et d'Alimentation,", 1918
      - Independence, 1930
    - Brazil - Order of the Southern Cross, 1822
    - France - Legion of Honor, 1802
    - Poland
      - "PTCK," Red Cross
      - Kosciuszko Squadron, Air Force
      - "Ameryki," Americans of Polish descent who fought in World War I
      - "Polania Restituta,", 1918
      - The Cross of Valor, 1920 August 11
    - Serbia
      - Red Cross
      - Order of Saint Sava, 1883
  - Medallions
    - Pius XI
    - Commemorating the first New York-Paris flight by Charles A. Lindbergh, "Spirit of St. Louis," New York, May 20 - Paris May 21, 1927
    - Swiss Confederation, Carnegie Foundation for Lifesavers, 1911 March 22
  - Scrapbooks (mostly of newspaper clippings) (Box 147)
    - Foreign Service - Latin America (mostly)
      - Appointments to Honduras, Havana and London
      - Assault made upon him in Havana by a Cuban journalist, Enrique Maza
        - 1912 August 27-September 2
        - 1912 September 2-12
        - 1912 September 14-December 30
        - 1913 February 5-August 27
    - Reviews of Gibson's book Belgium, The Country and Its People; his address to the Foreign Policy Association and the situation in Europe, 1939 July 13-December 15 (Box 148)
    - Preparatory Commission, Sixth Session, First Part, 1929 April-November
    - Book listing names of people mentioned in Gibson's letters to his mother, with corresponding dates, (matching card file in box 139), 1908-1914
    - Tripartite Naval Conference (Box 149)
      - 1927 June 19-July 11
      - 1927 July 9-August 3
      - 1927 August 2-8, November 17-December 17; 1928 January 13-March 28
    - London Naval Conference (Box 150)
      - 1929 December 27 - 1930 February 2
      - 1930 January 31-February 20
      - 1930 February 20-March 20 (Box 151)
      - 1930 March 19-April 11
      - 1930 April 11-April 25 (Box 152)
    - Conference of Experts for a Moratorium on Intergovernmental Debts, London, 1931
- MEMORABILIA (Memorabilia cabinet)
  - 1 leather bill-fold
  - 3 metal plates for printing of personal cards
  - 1 plastic plate (slab) with Gibson's signature
  - 7 printing blocks used for the book Hugh Gibson, 1883-1954 (light verse by Gibson in his handwriting)
  - Set of 8 overcoat and uniform buttons intended for Legation liveries in Warsaw, sent to Gibson by Reginald C. Foster in 1921
- SOUND RECORDINGS, 1930 (Record cabinet)
  Recording of the opening of the London Naval Conference by King George V (with the King's signature on the inside flap), January 21, 1930.
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Photo file)
  496 prints, 4 booklets of prints, 76 postcards, 4 negatives.
  - 1 print of Hugh Gibson, undated (Envelope mA)
  - 18 prints of Hugh Gibson, undated (Envelope mB)
  - 20 prints of Ynes Gibson (Mrs. Hugh) and 7 prints Ynes Gibson and others, undated (Envelope C)
  - 1 print of Hugh Gibson, John Foster Dulles, James T. Shotwell, and others, circa 1950; 1 print of members of the Commission for Relief in Belgium; 5 prints of children being fed (probably in Belgium); 1 print of Takashi Komatsu and family, 1937; 21 of unidentified house (probably in Brazil); 9 miscellaneous prints (Envelope mD)
  - 43 prints of Michael Gibson (son of Hugh Gibson), undated (Envelope E)
  - 1 print of Michael Gibson with Princess Josephine-Charlotte; 1 print of Astrid, Queen of the Belgians with Princess Josephine-Charlotte, undated (Envelope F)
  - 5 prints of Hugh Gibson and/or Mrs. Gibson with Michael Gibson; 3 prints of Mr. and Mrs. Hugh Gibson; 1 print of Michael Gibson's baptism, undated (Envelope G)
  - 1 print of wedding of Hugh Gibson and Ynes Reyntiens, February 27, 1922; 4 booklets of wedding prints (Envelope H)
  - 10 prints of Hugh Gibson and others; 2 prints of Hugh Gibson, Henry L. Stimson and others; 1 print of Herbert Hoover, Hugh Gibson and others, undated (Envelope I)
  - 38 prints of Spain during the civil war, 1936-1939 (Envelope J)
  - 1 print of Hugh Gibson addressing troops of General Josef Haller, Warsaw, Memorial Day, 1919; 3 prints of Hugh Gibson and Ynes Gibson, circa 1922; 1 print of Ynes Gibson and others, 1918; 1 scene in Bruges, Belgium, 1928; 1 print of family and friends of Ynes Reyntiens Gibson; 2 of Rev. John B. de Ville, 1932; 3 prints of Brussels, Belgium, 1927; 4 prints of members of the Belgian Royal family (Envelope K)
  - Trip to Latin America with the Intergovernmental Committee, 1952 August-September (Envelope L)
  - 61 prints of trip to Spain, 1939 (Envelope M)
  - 1 print of 2 soldiers in World War I; 1 print of Ynes Gibson and others, 1916 (Envelope mN)
  - 2 prints of Countess Sophie Clary (Foffa); 1 print of A. T. Ozoria; 1 print of Mary Gibson (mother of Hugh Gibson); 1 print of William Hallam Tuck and others, 1916; 1 print of the Clary family, 1923; 3 prints of Paula and Franzy Kinsky; 1 print of Capt. Clarence A. Abele, 1919; 1 print of the Sunset Club, 1945 (Envelope O)
  - 1 print of Baupre (?), 1913; 1 print of sketch of Herbert Hoover, 1933; 1 print of Grace Coolidge, (Mrs. Calvin); 1 print of Helena Paderewska (wife of Ignace), 1919 (Envelope mP)
  - 1 print of Hugh and Ynes Gibson, Pierre de Boal, Allen Winslow and other, Berne; 43 prints of the Legation in Warsaw, Poland, 1919-1922; 2 prints of Count Zamoyski and others; 10 scenes in Poland; 1 print of the Marquis de Villalobar, Cardinal Mercier, and others; 1 print of Cardinal Mercier and others (Envelope Q)
  - 66 postcards of France and Poland, 1919-1920; 1 postcard of Albert I, King of the Belgians; 1 post card of Leopold II, King of the Belgians; 3 postcards of General Jozef Haller; 5 post cards of Joseph Pilsudski; 1 print of Emperor Franz Josef (Envelope R)
  - 4 negatives, undated (Envelope S)
  - 30 unidentified prints, undated (Envelope T)
  - 8 unidentified prints, undated (Envelope U)
  - 28 unidentified prints, undated (Envelope V)
- CORRESPONDENCE II, 1912-1983 (Boxes 153-155)
  Consists of letters and telegrams, mainly sent to Ynes Gibson, as well as an address book and commemoratory materials after Gibson's death. Maintains the original arrangement of the creator.
  - Address book, undated (Box-folder 153: 1)
  - Letters to Ynes Gibson, 1912-1949
    - Clary, Countess Sophie (Foffa), 1912-1946 (Box-folder 153: 2)
    - 1922-1938 (Box-folder 153: 3)
    - 1937-1949 (Box-folder 153: 4)
    - 1939-1941 (Box-folder 153: 5)
    - 1945-1949 (Box-folder 154: 1)
    - Gibson, Hugh, 1932-1949
      - 1932 (Box-folder 154: 2)
      - 1938-1941 (Box-folder 154: 4)
      - 1942-1949 (Box-folder 154: 5)
  - Letters to Hugh and Ynes Gibson, 1933-1950 (Box-folder 154: 3)
  - General correspondence, 1914-1932 (Box-folder 155: 1)
  - Letters received by Ynes Gibson, A to M, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 155: 2)
  - Letters received by Ynes Gibson, M to Z, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 155: 3)
  - Intergovernmental Committee for Migration (ICM) ceremony honoring Gibson correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 155: 4)
    Includes ICM press packet and a speech by Michael Gibson.
- FAMILY FILE II, 1914-1955 (Box 156)
  Consists of correspondence, speeches, news clippings, announcements, and printed matter relating to Gibson's career and commemoratory after his death. Also included are diaries written by Ynes Gibson detailing her experince in World War I.
  - Ynes Gibson's diaries, 1914-1917 (Box-folder 156: 1)
  - South American tour journal, 1947 (Box-folder 156: 2)
  - Speeches and clippings on the death of Hugh Gibson and estate documents, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 156: 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE III, 1917-1947 (Box 156)
  Consists of letters and telegrams sent to and from the Gibson family.
  - Telegrams between Hugh Gibson and Mrs. Frank Gibson (mother), 1917-1924 (Box-folder 156: 4)
  - Letters to Michael Gibson, 1931-1947 (Box-folder 156: 5)
- PHOTOGRAPHS II, 1919-1954 (Box 157)
  Consists of photographs relating to Gibson's personal life and diplomatic career. Arranged chronologically by subject.
  - American legation and portraits from Warsaw, Poland, 1919 (Box-folder 157: 1)
  - Family, friends, colleagues, and miscellaneous photographs, 1922-1948 (Box-folder 157: 2-3)
  - Brazil, 1935 (Box-folder 157: 4)
  - ICM meeting in Geneva, circa 1954 (Box-folder 157: 5)
  - Prints of Herbert Hoover and Hugh Gibson, undated (Box-folder 157: 6)
  - One print of "Wake Up America!" with William Chenery, Fred Clark, Admiral Wm. V. Pratt, Mrs. Eve Garrette, and Hugh Gibson, undated (Box-folder 157: 7)
  - United States Embassy in London staff, undated (Box-folder 157: 8)
  - King Albert with family; one print of King Albert and Hugh Gibson, undated (Box-folder 157: 9)
- 2015 INCREMENT, circa 2015
  - "The Hoover for President Club" manuscript by Michael F. Gibson, circa 2015
    This family history is by Hugh Gibson's son. Per the author, "Writings of my parents are framed and reference is given to sources. Writings by their friends are signaled by a marginal line." The manuscript contains embedded color images; it is 479 pages. Received as a MS Word document titled THE_HOOVER_FOR_PRESIDENT_CLUB_FINAL.doc in 2015.
- APPENDIX
  List of items from the collection transferred to the Hoover Library.
  - All bound publications of the League of Nations regarding various disarmament conferences
  - Conference on the Limitation of Armament - Subcommittees, Washington, D.C., 1921-1922
  - Testament Politique du Cardinal Duc de Richelieu, Henri Desbordes, Amsterdam, 5th edition, 1696
  - Belgian newspapers
    - Le Temps Present, nos. 1-36 (not inclusive), 1914-1915
    - La Vie Universelle, no. 2
    - La Petite Illustration, 1921 March 3
  - Pamphlets
    - American Experiments in Disarmament and the London Conference of 1930, by William I. Hull, Committee on Peace and Service of Philadelphia Yearly Meeting of Friends, 12 p., 1929
    - Cost of Armaments, by William H. Gardiner, Navy League of the United States, 8 p., 1930 January 7
    - The Covenant of the League of Nations with a Commentary thereon, London: Majesty's Stationery Office, 19 p., 1921
    - Covenant of the League of Nations with Annex (French/English)
      - 18 p., 1928 December 1
      - 18 p., 1930 December 10
    - Final Protocol of the Locarno Conference (and annexes), together with Treaties between France and Poland, and France and Czechoslovakia, London: Majesty's Stationery Office, 1925
    - Fleet (the British Empire and Foreign Countries), London: Majesty's Stationery Office, 95 p., 1929
    - Investigation of Communist Propaganda, Report no. 2290, House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., 1931 January 17
    - Limitation and Reduction of Naval Armament, Treaty between the United States of America and Other Powers, Treaty Series, no. 830, Washington, D.C., 37 p., 1931
    - London Naval Conference, speeches and press statements by members of the American delegation, State Department Publication, Washington, D.C., 67 p., 1930
    - London Naval Treaty of 1930, State Department Publication, Washington, D.C., 23 p.
    - Memorandum ... of the Optional Clause of the Statute of the Permanent Court of International Justice, London: Majesty's Stationery Office, 13 p., 1929
    - Organisation et programme des cours, Ecole Libre des Sciences Politiques, Paris, 141 p., 1906-1907
    - Papers regarding the Limitation of Naval Armaments, London: Majesty's Stationery Office, 46 p., 1928
    - Parity in Naval Strength, by William H. Gardiner, Navy League of the United States, 12 p., 1930 January 11
    - Peace Treaty of Trianon, Society of Hungarian Lawyers, Budapest, 39 p., 1931
    - Photographic History of the Bolshevik Atrocities, 39 p., undated
    - Records of the Conference for the Limitation of Naval Armament, presented by Mr. Hale, 70th Congress, 1st session, Sen. Doc. No. 55, Washington, D.C., 220 p., 1928
    - Report of the Preparatory Commission for the Disarmament Conference and Draft Convention, State Department Publication, Washington, D.C., 102 p., 1931
    - Trade and Navies, by William H. Gardiner, Navy League of the United States, Washington, D.C., 11 p., 1930 January 9
    - The United States and the Other American Republics, Address by Henry L. Stimson, Secretary of State, Washington, D.C., 18 p., 1931
    - The Year's Major Factors in the Progress of Peace, Address by Charles E. Hughes, 71st Congress, 1st session, Senate Document no. 19, Washington, D.C., 11 p., 1929